A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Books and Reports Department, Subject Files FA935
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Books and Reports Department, Subject Files
1954-1976
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University Press
FA935
3.96 Cubic Feet 6 boxes and 3 packages.
6 boxes and 3 packages.
Biographical/Historical note
In order to assist in the dissemination of scientific investigations conducted at the Institute and elsewhere, publication was an early and important activity of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. A senior member of the scientific staff was usually the editor of a periodical. As early as 1910 the Institute had a Publication Service, which was supervised from 1910 by Editha C. Campbell until she retired in the fall of 1940. A Department of Illustration and Photography was under a part-time arrangement with De. Eduard Learning from 1906 until 1910 when Louis Schmidt undertook the direction of a full-time department. Louis Schmidt was at the head of the department until he reached the age of 70 in 1936. The work in the Department of Illustrations included hand-drawn illustrations for publications, photographs, moving pictures of experimental procedures made for the various investigators and used for a variety of purposes. Louis Schmidt served on a consultant basis until his death in 1939. Joseph Blauvelt Haulenbeek was acting in charge of Illustrations during that time and named officially in charge of illustrations in 1942, serving until he resigned September 1, 1946. Julian Alexander Carlile who was in charge of illustrations in the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology at Princeton took charge of the New York Department starting October 1, 1947 and divided his time between the two departments until they were consolidated during 1950. He directed the expanding department until his death in 1959 when he was succeeded by Richard F. Carter until 1964. In the academic year 1968/1969 Lewis William Koster became Manager of Graphic Services until 1973. March 1973 Bill Leyrer was appointed to that position.
Florence M. Stewart succeeded Editha Campbell in charge of the Publication Service in 1940 and served until she retired June 30, 1963, when she was succeeded by Margaret E. Broadbent.
Effective January 1, 1957 Charles Irvin Campbell was appointed Administrative Associate for Information Services. He had responsibility for a variety of information services among which were Secretary of the Library Committee, Librarian, ex officio, and supervision of the Publication Service and Illustration and Duplicating Services. Included were publication duties of such items as the Annual Report, Rockefeller Institute Quarterly, and the Calendar of Events. On October 20, 1958 the Board of Trustees approved a cooperative arrangement with the Oxford University Press to assist in producing, advertising and selling publications of the newly established Rockefeller Institute Press. The plan was for the Institute to continue publishing journals in accord with previously established policy and arrangements. Charles I. Campbell was appointed Director of The Rockefeller Institute Press. The Publications Service became the Journals Department without change of personnel or function. A new Books and Reports Department was created with responsibility for the production of books and the publication of bulletins and reports issued by the Institute.
January 1, 1960 Reynard F. Biemiller was appointed Assistant Director of The Rockefeller Institute Press. Effective December 5, 1960 Raymond B. Griffiths was appointed to the newly created position of Executive Editor of the Journal of Cell Biology.
Charles I. Campbell resigned May 15, 1962 and Joseph G. Sutton served as Acting Director of the Press from January 1963 until in 1964 William Arthur Bayless was named Director of the Press.
William Bayless retired as Director of The Rockefeller University Press on February 8, 1980. As of February 11, 1980, Mrs. Helene Jordan agreed to serve as acting director of the Press.
Effective July 1, 1980, Mrs. Helene Jordan was appointed Director of The Rockefeller University Press.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for scholarly research.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 530-3
Medical research; Biology -- Research; Medical technology; Medical education; Science -- Study and teaching; Medical sciences; Life sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Rockefeller University Press
- Convocation book, 1959 May 21-22
  Scope and Contents note
  Material collected for a book to be published which would be based on the proceedings of the first Academic Convocation, May 21-22, 1959 and the dedication ceremonies of the new buildings. The book was never published.
  - Master dummy (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Galley proofs and some photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Historical material on the various institutions represented. Biographical material and citations of the Honorary degree recipients (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Included are:
  - Giuseppe Gherardo Forni. University of Bologna. Presented by René J. Dubos (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Thomas Sherer Ross Boase. Oxford University Presented by George W. Corner (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Baron Adrian of Cambridge University. Presented by Peyton Rous (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jose Leon Barandiaran. University San Marcos of Lima. Presented by Richard E. Shope (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nabor Carrillo. University of Mexico. Presented by Paul A. Weiss (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nathan Marsh Pusey. Harvard University. Presented by Alfred E. Mirsky (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Presented by Detlev W. Bronk (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reprints of addresses given and later published in Nature (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lord Adrian. The place of science in universities past and present. Nature 183, 1959
    - Douglas M. Knight. The American college and the educated life. Nature 183, 1959
    - Henry Allen Moe. Role of the scholar in society. Nature l84 (also typescript), 1959
    - Detlev W. Bronk. A university of graduate studies. Nature 184, 1959
  - Publication plans (Box 1, Folder 4)
    News releases and various notes. Corrected typescript of addresses presented by Detlev Bronk, Wallace K. Harrison, architect and Barklie Henry, trustee at dedication of new buildings.
  - Editor's typescript working copies of published books, 1976 (Box 2)
    Helene Jordan was the University's editor working with the authors for the publication of Donald Griffin's THE QUESTION OF ANIMAL AWARENESS; EVOLUTIONARY CONTINUITY AND MENTAL EXPERIENCE and René Dubos' THE PROFESSOR, THE INSTITUTE AND DNA.
    Final typescript drafts were sent to the Archives Office by the editor.
    Arrangement note
    Arranged by author and page number.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Date received or inventoried: 1978
- Proceedings of the 50th anniversary (never published), 1954
  Biographical/Historical note
  The Occasion was held on 15 October 1954 and was marked by the naming of the existing buildings and breaking of the ground for new buildings. Invited speakers were Harry Emerson Fosdick who gave the Invocation; David Rockefeller who made some Introductory remarks; Detlev Wulf Bronk who introduced each of the speakers to follow. Eugene Lindsay Opie "The first laboratory of the Institute" Alan Mason Chesney "William Henry Welch" Peyton Rous "Simon Flexner" Richard Edwin Shope "Theobald Smith".
  Addresses were corrected and set in type; design was chosen and line drawings made but publication was never carried out.
  Material collected for a book to be published of the Proceedings on the Occasion of the Fiftieth Anniversary of the First Laboratory.
  Date received or inventoried: November 1979
  - Corrected typescript of various addresses (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Design of booklet, paper (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 2 sets of page proofs (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Corner, George W., 1889-. A history of The Rockefeller Institute, 1901-1953, origins and growth. New York, Rockefeller Institute Press, 1964. 635 p., 1961-1964
  The materials sent to the archives from the University Press consist of the typescript Press copy and various sets of galley proofs.
  File Plan note
  Old number: 530.3
  - Typescript press copy of manuscript
    - Chapters 1-2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Chapters 3, 4, 5 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Chapters 6, 7, 8 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Chapters 9, 10, 11 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Chapters 12, 13, 14 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Chapter 15 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Typescript press copy of manuscript
    - Chapters 16, 17, 18 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Chapters 19, 20 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Appendix 1, 2, 3 and Notes on Chapters (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - President's galley proof, 2 volumes in temporary binding
    - Text. President's galley copy in temporary binding with editor's corrections (Box 6)
    - 2 letters G. Corner to C.I. Campbell on proof corrections, 1960 July (Box 6)
  - Master set of 1st galley proof (Package 1)
  - 2nd galley proofs. Joseph Sutton working set 1961 Lay out pages for chapter headings dated 1964 (Package 2)
  - 3rd galley proofs Dr. Bronk's corrections (Package 3)